嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
所以, 今天我们将会有一期愉快的放松的视频, 我们只是在讨论
so, today we're going to have a nice chill episode, in which we just talk about
我们如何
how we're going to
将我们在之前写的代码抽象到一些类中
abstract some of the code that we've actually written in the past episodes out into some classes
这样我们就能更容易地使用它
so that we can use it more easily
当我们开始学习更复杂的OpenGL东西时
as we start to get into more complicated OpenGL stuff
这显然是这个系列前进的方向
which is obviously where this series is headed
因此, 在创建这个系列的过程中, 我确实提到过几次
so, I did mention a few times throughout creating this series
我真的不想把它制作成一个游戏引擎系列
that I really don't want to make this a game engine series
我不想让它像这样, 嘿, 我们要构建某种OpenGL引擎
I don't want to make it like, hey, we're going to build some kind of OpenGL engine
或者像是渲染引擎之类的
or like a rendering engine or anything like that
我真的不想花太多的时间来移动代码和设置东西
I don't really want to spend too much time moving code around and setting stuff up
让它绝对安全, 绝对完美
and making it absolutely bulletproof, and absolutely perfect
因为那不是这个系列的重点
because that's not the point of this series
这个系列只是我向你展示, 如何使用OpenGL
this series is just me showing you, how to use OpenGL
然而, 在现实世界中, 为了真正使用OpenGL
however, in the real world, in order to actually use OpenGL
你确实需要进行某种抽象, 因为你
you do need to perform some kind of abstraction of some sort, because you're
否则你就会得到一堆, 一堆乱七八糟的代码
otherwise you're just gonna end up having a pile, just a messy pile of code
那对你来说没什么意义, 它会非常冗长
that doesn't make much sense to you, it's gonna be extremely verbose
并且你会很难调试
and you're just gonna it's gonna be difficult to debug
有各种各样的问题
there's all sorts of issues
这对我向你展示来说是非常困难的, 举个例子
and it's gonna be extremely difficult for me to show you, for example
如何实现着色器映射
how to implement shader mapping
如果我在一个文件中做这些, 只有原始的OpenGL代码
if I'm all doing it in one file, with just raw OpenGL kind of code
因为这没有多大意义
because it's just it's not going to make much sense
所以, 在接下来的几期里, 我要做的是开始将代码移到类中
so, what I'm going to do over the next few episodes is, start moving code out into classes
向你展示, 我们如何移动公共代码
and showing you, how we can kind of I guess move common code around
这样我们就可以多次复用它
so that we can reuse it a lot of times
也可以把它参数化之类的
maybe parameterize it as well and all that stuff
这也是一个很好的机会来展示给我, 让我来给你们展示一下
it's also a really good opportunity to show me, a little bit of for me to show you guys a little bit about
比如, OpenGL如何被抽象
how like, how OpenGL can be abstracted
以及它在游戏引擎中是如何抽象出来的
and how like it typically would be abstracted in a game engine
虽然我们不打算深入讨论这个问题
even though we're not going to go as deep into this
就好像我实际上是在开发一个带有多个渲染接口的游戏引擎
as if I was actually writing a game engine potentially with multiple rendering apis
这将是相当简短和高水平的
it's going to be fairly like brief and high-level here
但这仍然是我展示给大家看的好机会
but still it's a really good chance for me to just show you guys
你通常会如何去抽象OpenGL
how you would typically go about abstructing OpenGL anyway
那么, 根据我们到目前为止所做的
so, out of what we've done so far
有一些东西我们需要转移一下
there are a few things that we need to actually move around
顶点缓冲区设置, 对吧, 索引缓冲区, 以及顶点数组
there's the vertex buffer set up, right, the index buffer set up, vertex arrays as well
以及我们是否想要使用它们
and whether or not we even want to use them
我想我在前一期中说过
I've said in the previous episode I think
我们将要用到的顶点数组
which was about vertex array that we will be using them
所以我们需要为它建立某种抽象
so we need to set up some kind of abstraction for that
然后是整个着色器的情况, 可能就是这样
and then there's the whole shader situation, that's probably it
如果你仔细想想我们目前所做的
like if you really think about what we've done so far
我们还没做过纹理之类的东西
we haven't done textures yet or anything like that
比如你知道的, 或者是帧缓冲之类的
or like you know frame buffers or anything like that
所以很明显我们没有一个完整的
so obviously it's not like we have a complete
就像OpenGL在这个主文件中实现的所有功能一样
like every feature OpenGL implemented in this main file
但它变得有点冗长了
but it is getting a bit lengthy
大概有200行代码
I think it's like about 200 lines of code
这就有点难以说清楚到底发生了什么
and it's getting a little bit hard to tell what's actually going on
并且也有点难读
and it's a little bit hard to read
但就我刚刚列出的这些来说
but in terms of what I just listed out there
顶点缓冲区, 索引缓冲区, 顶点数组, 着色器
vertex buffer, index buffer, vertex array, shader
这就是我们现在能抽象出来的所有东西
that's pretty much all we have right now that we can abstract
然而, 有一个东西需要将所有东西联系在一起
however, there is one thing that needs to tie everything together
那通常被称为渲染器
and that is traditionally known as a renderer
所以我们在某些时候也需要创建一个渲染器
so we do need to create a renderer at some point as well
使用渲染器的想法是相当简单的
and the idea with a renderer is fairly simple
你基本上就是给它一个命令, 它会为你渲染那个东西
you basically give it like a command, and it will render that thing for you
所以换句话说, 我想说
so in other words, I want to be able to say
嘿, 渲染器, 你能帮我绘制一下这个吗
hey, renderer, can you please draw me this
然后这个绘制函数可能会包含所有它需要的东西
and then the draw kind of function will potentially take in everything it needs to draw something
就是传统的顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区
which traditionally would be like a vertex buffer and index buffer
可能是任何类型的纹理, 任何渲染状态
potentially any kind of textures, any render states
就像你在blender的时候做的那样
such as like you do when blender on
我们是否应该写那种东西的深度
should we be writing to the depth of that kind of stuff
然后很明显, 我说的顶点缓冲, 索引缓冲, 比如材质, 着色器
and then obviously, what I say vertex buffer, index buffer, like materials, like a shader
也许是纹理之类的东西, 然后是所有的渲染状态, 对吧
maybe texture stuff like that, and then all the render states, right
所以这种渲染器的概念也需要存在
so that kind of concept of renderer needs to also exist
并且那对我们的实现非常重要
and that's gonna be extremely important for us to implement
所以我们今天要做的是, 只关注顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区, 这应该很简单
so what we're gonna do is today, just focus on vertex buffers and index buffers, which should be very easy
特别是因为我们决定使用顶点数组
especially because we've decided to use vertex arrays
所以我们不用担心实际顶点缓冲区的布局
so we don't have to worry about the layout of an actual vertex buffer
当我们写顶点缓冲类的时候
when we write that vertex buffer class
我们只关心实际的数据
we only care about the actual data
也就是一堆字节, 在这一点上很容易处理
which is just a bunch of bytes, really easy to deal with at this point
然后索引缓冲区基本上是一样的
and then the index buffer is basically the exact same thing
就像索引缓冲区和顶点缓冲区基本上是一样的
like literally index buffer vertex buffer basically the same thing
就抽象而言, 诸如此类
as far as the abstraction, and everything like that
然后在下一期, 我们可能会处理顶点数组
and then in the next episode, we'll probably deal with vertex arrays
在那之后可能就是着色器
and then after that probably shader
然后就是渲染器
and then after that maybe the renderer
那么一旦我们建立了所有的类集合
and then once we have all that kind of collection of classes set up
我们可以用它们来做一些相对简单的事情
we'll be able to actually use them to do things in a relatively easy way
在这个应用程序中, 这看起来应该非常简单
that should look very simple in this application
比如我们现在正要做的文件类
like file class thing that we have going on right now
所以那就是我们的计划
so that's the plan
让我们开始深入, 让我们开始抽象这些代码, 好了
let's dive in, let's start abtracting this code, okay
那么首先, 如果按f5运行
so first of all, if I just hit f5
我带你们看看我们现在的情况
so I can show you guys where we're at
当然, 这是我们在上一期讲到的
of course, is where we left off in the other episode
我们基本上只是创建了一个顶点数组
we basically just created a vertex array
以及如何制作矩形颜色的动画
and how to do this little animation of our rectangle color here
我今天主要要关注的是这个顶点缓冲区, 就在这里
the main thing that I'm going to be focusing on today is this vertex buffer which is right over here
也就是这个buffer, 它只接受这些浮点数的位置
which is called a buffer, and that's just taking in these float positions
差不多就是这样了
and that's pretty much it
然后当然还有索引缓冲区, 也就是这里的这个
and then of course the index buffer which is this thing here
现在这些顶点属性的东西
now this kind of stuff, this vertex attribute stuff
就是在顶点缓冲区的实际布局中
which is at the actual layout of our vertex buffer
那将在顶点数组类中处理
that's going to be dealt with in the vertex array class
所有这些在顶点数组类中可能最终也会把顶点缓冲区对象放入其中
and all of that in vertex array class will probably end up taking vertex buffer objects into it as well
因为我们通常会绑定顶点缓冲区
because we typically tie vertex buffer
我们通常在它们的布局中把顶点缓冲区绑定到实际的顶点数组
we typically tie vertex buffers with actual vertex arrays in their layouts
以及所有类似的东西
and all that kind of stuff
在那之后, 当然我们会处理着色器
and then after that of course we'll go with shaders
着色器会更复杂一些
shader is going to be a little bit more complicated
因为我们需要处理统一变量之类的问题
because we need to actually deal with uniforms and all of that
因此那一期应该会很有趣
so that should be a fun episode
但不管怎样, 今天, 很简单, 就出顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区
but anyway, today, nice and simple, vertex buffer and index buffer
我们该怎么做
how do we do that stuff
首先, 如果我们向上滚动到最上面, 你会看到一些东西
so first of all, if we scroll up to the very top, you'll see we have some stuff
这是相当常见的, 对吧
that's fairly common, right
比如这个错误检查, 这在OpenGL中是很常见的
like this error checking is stuff, that's kind of common to OpenGL right now
所以我要做的是在这个src目录上
so what I'm going to do is on the source over here
右键添加新项
I'm going to right click add new item
就添加一个头文件
I'm going to just add a header of file
我就叫它renderer
and I'm just going to call it renderer
再说一次, 我不想把它设置成游戏引擎之类的
again, I don't really want to set this up like a game engine or anything
所以我不会创建太多的类
so I'm not going to I'm going to try to create too many classes
所以我要保持这个简单明了
so I'll keep this nice and simple
我会把它放到渲染器类中, 它最终也会包含我们的渲染器
and I'll just put it into the renderer class, which will eventually contain our renderer as well
所以我也要创建一个cpp文件, 因为我们需要它
so I'm making a cpp file as well, because we need that
我们有一个Rendered.cpp和一个Renderer.h
so we have a Renderer.cpp and a Renderer.h
好了, 进入Renderer.h文件
okay, into the Renderer.h
我实际上要加入这个ASSERT, 这可能看起来不太直观
I'm actually going to put in this ASSERT, which might not seem very intuitive
因为断言通常会贯穿整个程序
because assertions are typically used throughout our entire program
不只是渲染器, 但它是可以的
not just the renderer, but it's okay
实际上, 我要复制粘贴所有这些东西
in fact, I'm just gonna copy and paste all of this kind of stuff
剪切它, 然后把它放到Renderer.h, 我刚刚不小心固定了它的工作
cut it and then put it into Renderer.h, which I just pinned accidentally works
很好, 酷, 这就是我们现在有的
okay, cool, so now this is what we have
我要包含一些东西
I'm going to include some stuff
现在我们显然是在输入这个gl
now we are obviously typing this with gl
所以在我们的渲染器头文件中包含glew是可以的
so it's okay to just include glew over here in our renderer a header file
然后我们还需要什么, iostream
and then what else we need, iostream
我们可能不需要这些东西
potentially we don't really need that stuff here
我不打算包含iostream
I'm not going to include iostream
我们只需要glew就行了, 好了, 酷
all we need is really just glew, okay, cool
那么现在这些东西, 我们要怎么处理这些东西
so now this stuff, what do we do with this stuff
我要做的第一件事就是取消静态
well the first thing I'm going to do is get rid of static
然后让它成为一个实际的声明而不是定义
and then just make it a an actual declaration rather than a definition
因为我们要把这个定义移动到实际的CPP文件中
because we're going to move that definition into the actual cpp file
所以我也会去掉GLLogCall的静态, 添加一个分号
so I'll get rid of static for GLLogCall as well, add a semicolon
实际上, 我们把这两个都复制一下
in fact, let's just copy both of these
我们要把它放进cpp文件
we're going to put it into the cpp file
在这里, 我将包含Renderer.h, 然后粘贴这个东西
in there, I'll include Renderer.h, and paste in this stuff
然后回到这里
and then back over here
我要像那样去掉这两个函数的函数体
I'm going to just get rid of the bodies of these two functions like that
好了, 看起来很简单
and there we go, okay, looks pretty simple
然后在Renderer.cpp中, 如果我们有那些东西
and then in Renderer.cpp, if we've got that stuff
让我们去掉这些分号
let's get rid of these semicolons
这里我们需要包含cout, 那么让我们包含iostream
now here we will actually need to include cout, so let's include iostream
这对我来说很不错, 好了
and that looks pretty good to me, okay
所以, 我们已经移出了常见的东西
so, we've moved out the kind of common stuff
我们可以在所有的类中包含Renderer
and we can just include renderer in all of our classes
如果我们真的需要访问这种GLCall宏
if we really need to get access to this kind of GLCall macro
以及它所做的一切以及断言, 很好
and everything that it does as well as ASSERT, cool
好了, 那么回到我们的应用
okay, so back our application
让我们看看我们这儿实际上需要移出什么
let's take a look at what we actually need to move out here
所以你可以马上看到GLCall, 给了我们一个错误
so straight away you can see GLCall,  course, is giving us an error
因为我们现在需要包含Renderer
because we now need to include renderer
因为我们需要映射, 然后我们向下滚动, 看看这个东西buffer
because we need the map, and then let's scroll down, and take a look at this buffer stuff
这就是我们需要的实际代码
so this is the actual code that we need
这就是一切
and that really is like all of it
我的意思是这个绑定缓冲区需要在某种绑定方法中被重用
I mean this bind buffer will need to kind of be reused in some kind of bind method
因为我们需要重新绑定不同的缓冲区
because we will have to rebind kind of different buffers as we go along
但是实际的创建只是生成缓冲区, 然后设置数据
but the actual creation is just gen buffers, and then setting the data
就是这样, 非常容易, 非常简单
that's it, really easy, really simple
那么在这个src目录, 右键添加新项
so on this source, I'm going to click right click add new item
应该是个头文件, 我就叫这个为VertexBuffer.h
gonna be a header file, and I'm going to call this VertexBuffer.h
然后为了cpp文件做同样的操作, VertexBuffer.cpp
I'm going to do the same thing for the cpp file, VertexBuffer.cpp
VertexBuffer.cpp会包含VertexBuffer.h
VertexBuffer.cpp is going to include VertexBuffer.h
右键这个VetexBuffer, 然后重命名为VertexBuffer
I'm also going to right click on VetexBuffer or VetexBuffer, and rename it to VertexBuffer
因为我刚才拼错了那个
because I did misspell that
好了, 酷, 现在当我回到我的头文件
okay, cool, now if I go back to my header file
输入class VertexBuffer
I'm going to type in class VertexBuffer
现在会有一个私有成员, 叫做unsigned int m_RendererID
going to have one private member just for now, called unsigned int m_RendererID
现在我说的是暂时的, 但它会永远这样
now I did say just for now, but it will have that forever
我的意思是, 我们暂时就这一个成员
what I meant is, we're just gonna add just one member for now
现在就这个m_RendererID, 对吧
now m_RendererID, right
让我们讨论一下这个
let's talk about this for a little bit
那么我们知道OpenGL需要某种数字id
so we know that OpenGL needs some kind of numeric id
在这个例子中, 它是一个无符号整数
in this case, it's an unsigned integer
这实际上是在跟踪什么
that actually kind of keeps track of what
基本上, 它就是一个id, 对于我们分配的每种类型的对象
it's an id, basically for every type of object we allocate
你知道的, 就像, 在OpenGL中创建, 对吧
you know, we like, create in OpenGL, right
所以当我创建纹理, 创建着色器
so if I create a texture, if I create a shader
当我创建顶点缓冲区, 索引缓冲区, 顶点数组, 帧缓冲区
if I create a vertex buffer, an index buffer, a vertex array, a frame buffer
不管怎样, 它都会得到某种id, 这个id是唯一的, 它是一个整数
whatever, it gets some kind of id, and that id is a unique id, that is an integer
它标识了特定的缓冲区, 或者我创建的特定对象
that identifies that specific buffer, or that specific object that I've created
那就是它的原理, 现在我就称这是一个渲染器id
that's how it works, now I am calling this a renderer id
因为其他的接口也可以在类似的系统上工作, 对吧
because other apis also work on a similar system, right
所以, 我在这里做的是让它保持通用性
so, what I'm really doing here is just kind of keeping it fairly generic
即使这是一个OpenGL系列教程
even though this is an OpenGL series
因此我把东西和OpenGL联系得很紧密
so I am tying things very closely to OpenGL
你知道的, 而不是叫这个OpenGL id, 或者就是id
you know, instead of just kind of kind of calling this OpenGL id, or just id
或者像, 我也不知道, 在叫它buffer之前是什么, 或者其他
or like, I don't know, what I called it before buffer, or whatever
渲染器id就是实际的内部渲染器id
renderer id is just the actual internal renderer id
所以如果你使用OpenGL作为渲染器
so if you're using OpenGL as your renderer
实际上, 这是与OpenGL相关的数字id
this is the numeric id that is actually relevant to OpenGL
因为我们可能有一个高级引擎方面的id
because we may have a high-level kind of engine side id
我们也像那样用它来表示对象
that we also use for objects like that
好了, 那么, 好吧, 我只是想解释一下我在这里做什么
all right, so, yeah, just just trying to explain what I'm doing here
因为我不打算让这个系列变得使我做起来比较艰难
because I'm not trying to kind of this series is going to be kind of tough for me to do
好吧, 现在我们就像这里的假墙一样被打破了
okay, now we're breaking like the false wall here
但无论如何, 这个系列对我来说还是有点难
but anyway, this series gonna be kind of tough for me to do
因为我想教你们OpenGL
because I'm trying to teach you guys OpenGL
但我还会把它和你可能使用OpenGL的方式混合在一起
but also I'm trying to mix it in with how you'll likely be using OpenGL
而这是两码事
and those are two different things
因为如果你看任何OpenGL教程, 它们会告诉你OpenGL的原理
because if you look at any OpenGL tutorial, they just show you how OpenGL works
那很好, 但那并不能告诉你如何在游戏开发中使用它
and that's great, but that doesn't tell you about, how to use it in a game
或者如何在一个引擎开发中使用它
or how to use it in an engine
或者如何在现实世界中使用它
or how to use it in the real world
我试着把这两者结合起来, 希望这会更有意义
I'm kind of trying to mix the two, I hope this makes sense
这显然是一个小例子, 但随着系列教程的继续
this is obviously a minor case, but as a series goes on
如果你有任何想法, 请在下方留言
if you have any thoughts, just leave a comment below
我会来帮你的
I'm here, I'm human, I'm here to help you
我想要改进这个系列, 就像你可能希望看到它们得到改进一样
I want to improve this series, as much as you probably want to see them improved
所以请在下方评论留下你的想法
so just leave your thoughts in the comments below
不管如何, 让我们回到这里吧
anyway, let's just get back to this here
那么, 我们有了一个渲染器id
so, we have a renderer id
我将在这里创建一个公共构造方法
I'm going to make a public constructor here
接收一个常量空指针data, 和一个无符号整型size, 好了
I'm going to take a constant void pointer data, and then an also an unsigned int size, okay
在这儿会有一个析构方法
we're going to have a destruct here
以及Bind和Unbind两个方法
and we're just going to have two functions Bind and Unbind
我现在喜欢添加这两个方法
I like to add these two now
当然, 在一个实际引擎中, 你会有一些其他方法, 比如设置数据
of course, in an actual engine, you will have other things like set data
可能会有锁定和解锁机制
maybe maybe have a lock and unlock mechanism
这样你就可以把数据流到顶点缓冲区
so that you can actually kind of stream data to the vertex buffer
当你在渲染的时候, 因为你不是在渲染
as you're kind of rendering, because you well not as you're rendering
但在你下次渲染之前
but before you render the next time
你可能想要修改顶点缓冲区
you might want to modify the vertex buffer
你可能会锁定它, 修改它, 解锁它, 做所有这些事情
and so you might kind of lock it, modify it, unlock it, and do all that kind of stuff
这里有很多你可以做的事情
there's a bunch of stuff you could do here
我们先把它简单化
we're going to keep it simple for now
运行当前程序所需要的只是绑定和取消绑定
all we need to run our current program is bind and unbind
随着这个系列的继续, 我们开始深入到更复杂的主题
as this series goes on, we start to kind of dive into more complicated topics
我们开始需要那些功能
and we start to require those features
我们将扩展这些类
we're going to just extend these classes
好了, 所以Bind和Unbind看起来不错
okay, so Bind and Unbind looks pretty good
我们也有构造和析构方法
and we have a constructor and a destructor
我觉得一切都很好
everything looks pretty good to me
那么现在回到我们的cpp文件
so now let's go back to our cpp file
实际上我要回到头文件
I'm actually going to go back to my header file
因为我要用视图辅助工具
and because I'm using visual assist
就是右键类名
I can just right click on the class name
转到快速动作并创建方法实现
go to quick actions and create method implementations
它会问我想要哪些
and it will ask me which ones I want
然后点击ok
then I can hit ok now
VS也会有这个
visual studio also does this
当你移动鼠标在这个类名上面
if you kind of hover your mouse over this and
我不知道, 按一个小箭头
I don't know, pressed a little arrow
你也可以为你的方法生成一般的实现
you can also generate stuff generally implementations for your methods as well
好了, 酷, 那这里我们要做什么
okay, cool, so what are we doing here
当我们回到我们的应用代码
if we go back to our application code
我们真正需要的是, 如果我复制这三行
all we really need is, if I copy these three lines
我要把它们放到这里
I'm gonna put them back over here
好了, 我们要包含我们的渲染器
all right, we're going to include our renderer
因为我们需要这些GLCall宏
because we need that for these GLCall macros
然后代替buffer的是, 我们的m_RendererID
and then instead of buffer, it's going to be our m_RendererID
然后代替positions的是data
and then instead of positions, it's going to be data
以及代替这个的是size
and instead of this thing, it's going to be size
那就是我们所需要的
and that's really all we need
现在我要复制这个绑定缓冲区
now I'm going to copy this bind buffer
把它放入Bind和Unbind中, 除了unbind
and put it into bind and unbind, except with unbind
我就让它为0, 好了
I'm going to make it zero, okay
非常简单, 非常直接
pretty simple, pretty straightforward
我们还要添加的一个操作就是删除这个顶点缓冲区
one more thing we're going to add here is of course the deleting of this vertex buffer
所以就是GLCall(glDeleteBuffers)
so I'm just going to write GLCall glDeleteBuffers
我们会删除一个缓冲区, 它会是我们的m_RendererID
we're going to delete one buffer and it's going to be our m_RendererID
好了, 就这样
okay, that's it
这就是我们的整个顶点, 这很简单
that is our entire vertex, as how simple is that
现在让我们对索引缓冲区重复同样的操作
now let's repeat the same thing for an index buffer
现在因为这些类非常相似
now because these classes are so similar
我实际上要打开这个包含文件夹
I'm actually just going to open this containing folder
我将复制粘贴这个VertexBuffer
and I'm going to literally copy and paste this VertexBuffer
这两个文件头文件和cpp文件
both of these files header file and the cpp file
只是重命名IndexBuffer
and just rename them to IndexBuffer
因为它们是如此的相似
because that's how similar they are
好了, 回到VS, 点击这个小按钮来刷新这个
okay, back in virtual studio, hit this little button here to refresh this
你可以看到我们有两个新文件
you can see we have two new files
选择两者, 右键单击包含在项目中
select both of them, right click include in project
然后我们开始重构它们
and then let's start refactoring them
那么这是一个索引缓冲区, 现在渲染器id保留在那儿
so this is an index buffer, now renderer id stays there
我们唯一需要的另一个成员实际就是m_Count
the only other thing we need is an actual m_Count
因为我们需要知道, 这个实际上有多少个索引
because we need to know, how many indices this actually has
我将用IndexBuffer替换这个, 当然是代替VertexBuffer
I'm going to replace this with IndexBuffer, of course instead of VertexBuffer
至于这个常量空指针data
const void point data
现在, 我们暂时将支持32位索引
now, for now we're going to support 32 bit indices
我不知道是否有必要在这里加上16位索引, 尤其是在这个系列中
I don't know if it's even worth adding 16 bit indices at this point especially in this series
只要知道你可以有不同的整数类型
just know that obviously you can have different integer types
对于你的索引缓冲区, 可以有不同整数大小
different integer sizes for your index buffer
或者可以是16位整型, 比如短整型, 无符号短整型
or you can have 16 bit integers, so like shorts, unsigned shorts
你也可以用32位整型
you can have 32 bit as well
注意, 我就用32位的
look, I'm just gonna use 32 bit
我不认为我们有理由同时支持这两种, 真的
I don't think there's a reason for us to support both, really
当然, 从理论上讲, 使用16位整数有性能优势
of course, theoretically there are performance benefits to using 16 bit integers
如果你没有, 如果你
if you don't, if you're
如果你正在绘制3D模型
if you're 3D model that you're drawing
没有那么复杂, 没有那么多三角形
isn't like that complex, doesn't have that many triangles
它需要超过76,535个不同或65,536个不同的索引
that it requires more than 76,535 different or 65,536 different indices
但是我们还是简单点吧, 就用无符号整型
but we're just gonna keep it simple, unsigned int
那么就是常量无符号整型data
so const unsigned int data
现在, 因为我们提供了一个无符号整型, 而不是空类型
now, because we've supplied an unsigned int and not a void
我们没有必要使用字节大小
there's no point for us really taking a byte size
我们想要的是统计
what we instead want is the count
那么, 现在我们提供了多少个索引
so how many indices are we supplied now
我喜欢用size和count来区分这两个词
I like to distinguish these two by using the words size and count
当我写size时, 当我创建一个变量size时
when I write size, when I create a variable called size
它几乎总是以字节为单位
that is almost always in bytes
如果因为某种原因, 它不是, 它们可能会
if for some reason, it's not, they'll probably
我肯定会留下注释什么的
I'll definitely leave a comment or something
但是像在实际的源代码中
but like in the actual source code
但是size表示字节数, count表示元素数
but size means bytes, count means element count
所以换句话说, 如果我正在绘制这个正方形
so in other words, if I have, if I'm drawing the square
我知道那个有六个索引, 对吧
and I know that's six indices,  right
6个索引意味着如果我写数字6
six indices that means if I write the number 6
那就是统计, 对吧, 我没有写6乘以4, 等于24
that's the count, right, I don't write six times four, which is 24
那会是size, 24是size, 6是count
that will be the size, 24 is a size, 6 is a count
明白吧, 那就是我们需要的
okay, and that's all we need here
让我们回到这个实现文件
let's go back to this implementation file
现在我要点击这里的control h, 调出这个查找和替换
now I'm going to just hit control h over here, to bring up this find and replace thing
我将用IndexBuffer替换VertexBuffer
I'm going to replace VertexBuffer with IndexBuffer
然后按alt a来替换当前这个文件中的所有内容
and then hit alt a to replace all in this file current
确保它在当前文档中
make sure it's in current document obviously
我们继续
and there we go
现在我要把这个去掉, 用原来的替换掉
so now I'll get rid of this, and replace it with what I had there
视觉辅助工具能帮我处理这个问题
which visual assist can help me out with again
最后, 就是这里替换size和data
and then finally instead of size and data here
我要写, 主要是替换size
I'm going to write, instead of size primarily
它会是count乘以sizeof(unsigned int)
it's gonna be count times sizeof unsigned int
现在这里可能有些危险
now there may be some danger here
因为我假设unsigned int的大小和GLunit是一样的
because I'm obviously assuming that the size of an unsigned int is the same as GLunit
因为我不想用那个
because I'm specifically not using that
平台差异, 我从未见过, 和unsigned int之前没有用它, 老实说
platform differences I've never seen, and unsigned int not before by its, to be honest
是的, 就像从来没有
yeah, like never
你所在的平台可能不是这样, 记住那件事
you might be on a platform where it's not, keep that in mind
我不喜欢使用OpenGL的那个
I don't really like using the OpenGL one
所以这里我还是写unsigned int
so I'm still gonna write unsigned int here
但记住那点
but just keep that in mind
在运行时, 你甚至可能需要完全谨慎
you may want to even be completely cautious at runtime
还有可能检查一下
and potentially check to see
sizeof(unsigned int)实际上是否等于sizeof(GLuint)
if the sizeof an unsigned int is actually equal to the size of a GLuint
确保你使用的是类型, 对吧, 而不是实际的
make sure you use the type, right, not the actual like
不要写GLunsignedint, 因为那不是一种类型, 一定要写GLuint
don't write GLunsignedint, because that's not a type, make sure you write GLuint
但你使用那个可能要非常小心
but you may want to be like really cautious with that
但无论如何, 我将使用unsigned int
but anyway, I'm just gonna use unsigned int
我们需要替换的另一个东西是ARRAY_BUFFER
the other thing we need to replace is ARRAY_BUFFER
变成ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
becomes ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
就是这样
that's really it
我的意思是, 如果我往下写
I mean if I go down here
这里我要把绑定缓冲区这里, 改成ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
I'm just going to write bind buffer here to be ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
就这样
and that's it
在某种程度上, 我们显然还需要做的另一件事是count
the other thing we obviously need to do is still count somehow
所以我要在这里写一个初始化列表
so I'm going to write an initialized list here
它设置count为count, 就像这里一样
that just sets count to count like that up here
最后是一个获取器
and then finally a getter
inline unsigned int GetCount() const, 返回m_Count
inline unsigned int GetCount const, return m_Count
实际上我还会把Bind和Unbind标记为const
I'm actually also going to mark Bind and Unbind as const
因为它们实际上不会修改任何东西
because they don't actually modify anything
以后我们可能会在const对象上调用它们
and we'll probably want to call them on const objects in the future
顶点缓冲区也一样, 因此顶点缓冲区Bind和Unbind标记为const
same for the vertex buffer as well, so vertex buffer Bind and Unbind are becoming const
好了, 继续, 就这样了
okay, there we go, so that's it
那就是抽象那两个的全部内容
that's really all there is to abstracting those two
让我们继续替换我们在Application.cpp文件中已有的代码
let's go ahead and replace the code that we've got in the Application.cpp file
用这种我们创建的新类
with this new kind of these new classes that we've created
抱歉, 回到Applicatiop.cpp, 我要把它们都包含在顶部
sorry, back in Application.cpp, I'm going to include both of them at the top here
那么包含VertexBuffer和IndexBuffer
so include VertexBuffer and include IndexBuffer
然后向下滚动
and then I'm going to scroll down here
然后当我们实际上创建这个VertexBuffer时
and then when we actually create this VertexBuffer
我要删除所有这些代码, 然后写一个VertexBuffer
I'm just going to delete all this code, and write a VertexBuffer
我不打算把它全部删除
I'm actually not going to delete all of it
因为我需要复制一部分
because I'll need copy parts of it
写一个VertexBuffer vb()
I'll try a VertexBuffer vb
我们把这个作为size, 然后把positions作为data
we're going to write this as the size, and then positions as the data
那么就是positions和那个size, 好了, 漂亮
so positions and then that size, there we go, beautiful
现在我们在这里自动绑定它了
now we actually bind it automatically here
如果我们看一下我们写的代码中的顶点缓冲区
if we look at the vertex buffer in the code we actually wrote
我们从未解绑它
we never unbind it
我们让它保持绑定
we just leave it bound
理论上我们不需要调用vb.Unbind()
so theoretically we don't need to call vb Unbind
在我们这样做之后, 因为它已经被绑定了
after we do this, because it will already be bound
但很明显, 如果我们有多个, 比如我们创建一些像这样的
but obviously if we have multiple like if we create a few like this
我们必须重新绑定我们想要使用的那些
we'll have to rebind the ones that we want to use
但这将由顶点数组来处理
but that'll be handled by the vertex array
无论如何, 因为顶点数组是与顶点缓冲区相关联的
anyway, since the vertex array is associated with a vertex buffer
当我们开始跟踪抽象顶点数组时
and when we start up track abstracting the vertex array
我们会看到那个是如何处理的, 好了
we will see how that works, okay
那么回到这里, 我们会对索引缓冲区做同样的事情
so back here, we're gonna do the same thing for index buffer
那么IndexBuffer ib(), indices就是实际的缓冲区
so IndexBuffer ib, indices is the actual buffer
然后代替6*sizeof(unsigned int), 我们只需要写6
and then instead of six times sizeof unsigned int, we just need to write six
so IndexBuffer ib, indices is the actual buffer
然后代替6*sizeof(unsigned int), 我们只需要写6
and then instead of six times sizeof unsigned int, we just need to write six
因为我们知道提供的是无符号整数, 好了, 很好
because we know we're supplying unsigned ints, okay, beautiful
把那些也都去掉
get rid of all that as well
这里只剩下实际的顶点数组了
the only thing we leave here is the actual vertex array stuff, right
顶点缓冲区布局之类的东西
the vertex kind of buffer layout stuff
但除此之外, 那就是我们现在需要的
but other than that, that's really all we need now
最后, 不把它绑定在这里, 我们只写vb.Bind()
finally instead of binding this here, we just write vb.Bind
然后绘制元素, 理论上你可以把它放到索引缓冲区中
and then draw elements is something that you could theoretically put into your index buffer
问题是, 就像通常的工作方式一样, 你会
the thing is, like the way that this usually works is that you will
比如你有一个复杂的3D模型, 比如宇宙飞船, 对吧
like if you have a complex 3D model, like a spaceship, right
你可能会有一个顶点缓冲区
you will probably have a vertex buffer
它包含了飞船的每个顶点
that just contains every single vertex of that spaceship
那可能是相当大的
and that might be like fairly big
但是你可能会有几个索引缓冲区, 它们会绘制出飞船的一部分
but then you may have several index buffers, that draws parts of that ship
因为机翼的材料可能与实际的玻璃座舱不同
because the wings will probably be a different material than the actual glass cockpit, right
所以当你画驾驶舱窗户的时候
so the cockpit glass when you draw the cockpit windows
可能是一种玻璃材料
there'll probably be like a glass material
而机翼可能是金属材料
whereas the wings might be a metal material
所以你必须将它们分成两个不同的绘制调用
so you'll have to split them up into two different draw calls
通常的方法是你有一个索引缓冲区
and the way that you'll usually do that is you'll have an index buffer
只绘制机翼
that just draws the wings
还有一个索引缓冲可以绘制真正的玻璃, 比如驾驶舱玻璃之类的东西
and an index buffer that just draws the actual glass, like cockpit glass and all that stuff
我们以后会详细讨论那个
and we'll definitely talk more about that
当我们开始加载3D模型并开始渲染真实的东西时
when we start loading 3D models and start rendering stuff for reals
但那只是一个基本的例子, 正因为如此
but that's just a basic example, and so because of that
你仍然有一个顶点缓冲区
you still have the one vertex buffer
然后你有几个索引缓冲区, 它们被索引到顶点缓冲区中
and then you have several index buffers, that are just indexed into that vertex buffer
你能做的就是
and so what you could do is
把你的绘制, 你的元素绘制,  你实际的绘制调用绑定到你的索引缓冲区
you could tie your drawer, your drawer elements, your actual draw call to your index buffer
因为从理论上讲, 索引缓冲区是这样的, 那就像, 好吧
because theoretically the index buffer is kind of the thing, that's like, okay
我把它绘制成, 像从这个偏移量开始的这些索引
I'm going to draw the, like this many indices starting at this offset
诸如此类的东西
and all that kind of stuff
我们实际不打算那么做
we're not actually going to do that
因为我们会让渲染器来处理实际的绘制调用
because we're going to let the renderer take care of the actual draw call
当我们扩展渲染器类实际上会接收
so when we extend our renderer class to actually take in
你知道, 就像, 我想画点什么
you know, like, I want to draw something
我给你提供了一个顶点缓冲和索引缓冲以及材质, 所有这些东西
I'm supplying you with a vertex buffer and index buffer and material, all that stuff
它只会查看索引缓冲区, 然后问它
it will just look at the index buffer, and ask it
count是多少, 然后自身发出DrawCall指令
what the count is, and then issue the DrawCall itself
所以那就像
so that's just like
如果你关心为什么我不把绘制元素放到索引缓冲区
if you're concerned about why I'm not putting draw elements into the index buffer
你就会看到之前那样
and you've seen that before
这就是为什么, 因为我会让渲染器类来处理这个
that's why, because I'm actually just gonna let the renderer class take care of that
好了, 酷, 如果我们按f5, 来验证我们的代码是否还能运行
okay, cool, so if we hit f5, just now to verify that our code actually still works
因为那是很重要的
because that's important
你可以看到, 现在一切都很好
you can see it does and everything's great now
给你个小提示, 我已经准备好了一个小提示
quick little tip here, I'm already a tip of thought
如果我们关闭这个, 你会看到我们的应用不会终止
if we close this, you can see our application doesn't terminate
如果我们点击暂停，暂停调试器，看看发生了什么
and if we hit pause over here, to just pause the debugger, and see what's up
你可以看到一些GLClearError
you can see some GLClearError
让我们看看核心堆栈, 看看这里发生了什么
let's look at the core stack and see what's going on here
所以我们调用GLClearError, 它看起来像一个无限循环
so we're calling GLClearError, it looks like it's an infinite loop
它来自IndexBuffer析构方法
and it's coming from IndexBuffer destructor
来自主函数
which is coming from main
这是因为它试图清理所有堆栈分配的对象
that's because it's trying to clean up all of our stack allocated objects
否则这个索引缓冲区, 它会试图清理
and otherwise this index buffer, it's trying to clean that up
现在的问题是
now the thing with this is that
你可以看到这是一个堆栈分配的对象
you can see that this is a stack allocated object
因此, 它的析构方法在作用域退出时被调用
so its destructor is called when the scope exits
也就是主函数的末尾
which is of course at the end of this main function
然而我们调用glfwTerminal会破坏之前的OpenGL上下文
however we call glfwTerminal which destroys our OpenGL context before that
所以实际发生的是
so what's actually happening is
我们现在不再有一个有效的OpenGL上下文和GLCheckError
we now no longer have an OpenGL a valid OpenGL context and GLCheckError
信不信由你, 如果没有上下文, 我们会返回一个OpenGL错误
believe it or not, we'll return an OpenGL error, if there is no context
这就是为什么我认为OpenGL比较搞笑的原因之一
this is why one of the reasons why I think OpenGL is just comedy
但是, 是的, 检查错误函数将返回一个错误
but, yes, the check error function will return an error
如果没有有效的OpenGL上下文
if there's no valid OpenGL context
因为OpenGL本身告诉你, 你应该在循环中运行这个
and since OpenGL itself tells you, hey, you should be running this in a loop
每次调用它, 它都会返回一个错误, 所以这是一个无限循环
every time you call it, it'll return an error, so it's an infinite loop
要解决这个问题, 你可以做的一件事就是从堆分配
so one thing you could do to fix this is of course heap allocate
你实际的顶点数组
your actual vertex array which you
抱歉, 是你的顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区
sorry, your vertex buffer and your index buffer
然后删除它
and then deleted it
在你的glfw结束之前, 这可能是你应该做的
before your glfw end of your turn now which is what you probably should do
不管怎样, 实际上, 很少看到它们被很好地分配到栈上
anyway, it's very rare to see them actually be stack allocated well
是的, 可能很少看到它们被分配堆栈
yeah, it's probably rare to see them be stack allocated, anyway
所以, 我们在这里实际上可以做的, 从技术上来说
so, what we can do here is actually well, technically speaking
我们可以创建这些指针, 然后使用new分配它们
we could just make these pointers, and allocate them using new
然后显式地删除它们, 就像这里, 在我们使用glfwTerminate之前
and then delete them explicitly like over here, right, so before we glfwTerminate
这样我们的问题就解决了
and that would fix our problem
然而, 这是一种独特的情况
however, this is kind of a unique case
因为我们实际上是在主函数作用域中创建顶点缓冲区, 这是非常罕见的
because we're actually making vertex buffers in the main function scope, which is very rare
我们可以做的另一件事就是创建一个新的作用域
another thing we could do obviously just create a new scope
所以这也是一种解决方法
so here's one way to fix it
我要在这个positions周围创建一个作用域
I'm going to make a scope around this positions thing here
只是把所有东西最小化
and have it whoops just minimize everything
我要在就像这个positions之前创建作用域
I'm going to create scope around like just before this positions thing
然后像这样结束, 像这样, 好了
and then have it end like over here like that, okay
所以有点看不清楚, 但如果我把它缩小, 可能会更容易看清楚
so it's a bit hard to see, but if I zoom out, maybe it'll be easier to see
尽管文本非常小, 你可以看到
even though the text is really tiny, you can see
我在这里做了一个作用域, 它在这里结束
I've made a scope over here and it ends kind of over here, right
所以理论上它应该包含所有的东西
so theoretically that should contain everything
那么如果我现在按f5运行我的代码
so if I just hit f5 to run my code now
希望没有变量在作用域外面
hopefully we haven't got any variables outside
好了, 编译正常, 所以现在一切都在运行
okay, I'm good at compiles, so everything's running now
然后点击关闭, 你会看到应用实际上终止了
and then if I hit close, you can see the application actually terminates
这只是我想说的一个小问题, 只是为了解决这个问题
that was just the quick little thing I wanted to throw in, just to fix that
因为当我们关闭它时, 这有点烦人, 它实际上没有终止
because that was a bit annoying when we closed it, and it didn't actually terminate
所以我们不得不终止一个第三方VS, 这很烦人
so we had to terminate a three visual studio which is annoying
但不管如何, 就是这样
but, anyway, that's it
那么我们抽象了顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区类
so, we've abstracted the vertex buffer and the index buffer class
我认为这一期相当随意, 可能讲得很快
I think this episode was fairly casual, probably talked pretty quickly
但那是因为这个东西真的很简单
but that's because this stuff is really straightforward
我希望你能理解我所做的一切
and I hope you understood everything that I did
这里也有一些随机的想法
there were some random thoughts here as well
如果你喜欢这个视频, 就点个赞, 让我知道你对它的看法
let me know what you thought of the video by just dropping a like, if you liked it
然后留下评论, 就像这样
and leaving a comment,  and like just being like
伙计, 这太可怕了
hey, man, this was like terrible
你应该停止在YouTube上的这一切, 这可能不会
you should stop this whole YouTube thing, which probably wouldn't be
不管怎样, 下次, 我们会抽象着色器类
anyway, next time, we're going to abstruct the shader class
我知道, 我们会先做顶点数组类, 还有着色器类
I actually know, we're gonna do the vertex array class first, and the shader class
然后可能是渲染器
and then probably the renderer
你们喜欢我的这些视频
you guys like these videos of mine
你想要支持我在YouTube上做的c++系列和OpenGL系列
and you want to support what I do here on YouTube with c++ series and OpenGL series
还有即将到来的游戏引擎系列
and the soon to come game engine series which is actually coming very soon
顺便说一句, 然后你可以直接去patreon.com/TheCherno
by the way, then you can head on over to patreon.com/TheCherno
帮助支持这个系列以及我所做的一切
and contribute to helping support this series and everything that I do
你会得到一些很酷的奖励
and you'll get some cool rewards
我们将有每周, 抱歉, 每月的伙伴聚会
we're about to have the weekly partner, sorry, the monthly partner hang-out
我想这周我们基本上就会有聚会
and I think this week actually, well we basically just hang-out
我们谈论的都是合作伙伴级别的赞助人
and we talk like, all of the partner level tier patron patrons thing we hang-out
然后我们就聊了一个小时
and we just talk about stuff for like an hour
那应该很有趣
that should be pretty fun
还有其他一些很酷的奖励
there's some other cool rewards
比如一期接一期地访问所有的源代码
such as access to all of this source code kind of episode by episode
emmm...对
um yeah
非常感谢你们
thank you huge
再次感谢所有的赞助人
thank you again to all the patrons
因为没有他们, 就没有这个系列
because this series would not be here without them
下次见, 拜
and I will see you next time, goodbye